Guide to the Charles Prentice Howland Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Charles P. Howland Papers, 1916-1932; Series III; 2.5; (7 boxes)
  - Topical files
    - Mexico
      - Mixed claims, 1922-1931, undated (Box 9, Folder 188-191)
      - General notes, 1926-1932, undated (Box 10, Folder 192-194)
      - Mexican Agrarianism and the U.S., undated (Box 10, Folder 195)
    - Notes on China and Japan, 1929, undated (Box 10, Folder 196-197)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 198-202)
    - Printed material
      - Agrarian reform, 1923-1931, undated (Box 10, Folder 203-204)
      - Dept repudiation, 1919-1931 (Box 11, Folder 205-206)
      - Mexico, 1916-1931 (Box 11, Folder 207-209)
      - Miscellanea, 1921-1931, undated (Box 11, Folder 210-211)
    - Outline on Japan, undated (Box 11, Folder 212)
    - Repudiated state debts, 1927-1930 (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - "Sedgewick Papers", 1927-1928, undated (Box 11, Folder 214-216)
    - Study of economic sanctions, 1930-1931 (Box 12, Folder 217-218)
    - Thessalonica Institute, undated (Box 12, Folder 219)
    - Miscellanea
      - Welles, Graham, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 220)
      - Clippings, 1916-1925 (Box 12, Folder 221)
      - Unidentified, 1924, 1926, 1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 222-223)
- Legal and Business Papers, 1809-1893, undated; Series IV; 0.5; (1 box)
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Legal and business papers, 1809-1893. undated (Box 13, Folder 224-250)
- Bills and Receipts, 1841-1901; Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  - Bills and receipts, 1841-1901, undated (Box 14, Folder 251-294)
- Additional Material, 1883-1956, 1972, 1981-1983, undated; Accession 1992-M-018; .5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1992 Jan
  Received from: Esther H. Montgomery, 1991 Sep 10
  Typed transcriptions for much of the correspondence were received with the papers and were retained for the convenience of researchers.
  - Correspondence of Virginia Howland
    - A - D, 1933-1934, 1949, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - F, 1933, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - H - L, 1929, 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Howland, Charles P., 1917 September-October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jaccaci, August F., 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - M - S, 1933, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mitrany, David, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Salter, Arthur, 1929-1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence of Charles P. Howland
    - B - H, 1922, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Burlingham, Charles C., 1919, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Davis, Homer
      See: box 1, folder 26
    - Fraenkel, Osmond, 1932
      See: box 1, folder 13
    - Frankfurter, Felix, 1924-1932 Nov, n.y. (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - Furniss, E. S., 1929
      See: box 1, folder 12
    - Hale, Richard W., 1932
      See: box 1, folder 13 box 1, folder 14
    - Howland, Henry E., 1896-1909 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Jay, Pierre
      See: box 1, folder 14
    - L - M, 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Laski, Harold, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lippman, Walter, 1928, 1932
      See: box 1, folder 13 box 1, folders 12
    - S - T, 1906, 1929-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Salter, Arthur, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Wainhouse, David W.
    - Zimmern, Alfred, 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subject files
    - Acknowledgements of gifts, 1933, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "America and India" clippings, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - American Consular Service: original document and translation of a resolution of committees of refugee settlements in Greece, 1926 September-December (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Argonne Association of America, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Athens College, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Athens College: Howland Prize Speaking Contest and scholarship fund, 1933 January-February (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Book reviews by C.P. Howland, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence of others, 1925, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Death of Charles P. Howland: letters of condolence, memorials, clippings, 1932-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Emergency Unemployment Relief Committee, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Memorandum of conferences with Stimson and Cotton at Washington, 1930 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mooney, Tom: Molder's Defense Committee, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1926-1930, 1972, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Printed material, 1921, 1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "A Project to Study the Socio-Legal Problem of the Failure of Family Support in Families Divided Between Countries by Migration," International Migration Service, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Quotations, notes, 1912-1918, 1924-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Rip Van Winkle", 1883 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified script, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Yale College: graduation invitation, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Writings, speeches
    - "The Anglo-American Naval Controversy", 1928 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "The Anglo-American Naval Question": report, 1929 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Anglo-American relations: untitled writing, 1929 February 25 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Armistice Day address, 1932 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "The Cult of Nationalism", 1932 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Depression philosophies and selected quotations, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "Estimation of the German Character: from the Report by Geoffrey Young", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "The Failure of Farm Board Stabilization", 1932 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "The Foreign Policy of the United States: Suggestions for an Immediate Program", 1921 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Foreign Relations of the Next Administration", 1928 April (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Franco-British accord on disarmament: statement, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "The Freedom of the Seas", 1929 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Greek refugees: article pertaining to, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - International conferences: untitled speech pertaining to, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "Kaltchas Essay": notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "League enthusiasts": notes, [1929?] (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Milton Academy: commencement address, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - National League of Women Voters: speech on disarmament, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Notes for a Talk on the Kellogg-Briand Treaty", 1928 November (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Notes on Security and Disarmament": outline, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "Our Repudiated State Debts", 1928 April (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Outlawry of war: untitled paper, [1929?] (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "Politics and Ships at London", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "The Present and Future of Anglo-American Relations", 1929 July (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "1787-1919: A Comparison in the Psychology of the Opponents of the Constitution and of the League of Nations", 1920 January 3 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Should the League Use Military Force?", 1922 October 6 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "The Spirit of Youth": alumni dinner speech, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Vanishing Greek Brigandage", [192?] (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Yale graduates: speech pertaining to, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Writings, speeches of others
    - Frankfurter, Felix: remarks by, 1949 October (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Salter, Arthur: speech, 1931 September 23 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Additional Material, 1852-1937, undated; Accession 1994-M-013; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1994 May
  Received from: David Howland, 1993 Jul 28
  - Howland, Henry Elias
    - "The Little Boy who Went Out to Swim," St. Nicholas, 1874 September (Box 1)
    - Poems by H. E. Howland and others, 1852, undated (Box 1)
    - Yale Banger incident, with accompanying correspondence, 1852, 1927 (Box 1)
    - "Memorial of Henry E. Howland", by Henry A. James, 1914 (Box 1)
    - Bills of sale, receipts, calling cards, 1852-1856, undated (Box 1)
    - Class of 1854 album (2 copies) (Box 1)
    - Photograph album, primarily of family members, Henley Regatta, and Panama Canal, undated (Box 1)
    - Scrapbooks (2 vols): clippings, correspondence, poems, 1870s-1920s (Box 2)
  - Howland, Charles Prentice
    - "A Disastrous Football Game", undated (Box 3)
    - "What Might Have Been": poem in Harper's Monthly Magazine, undated (Box 3)
    - Survey of Foreign Relations, with annotated card reading "Very first copy", 1931 (Box 3)
    - "In Memoriam, C. P. Howland": album with items laid in, 1932-1937 (Box 3)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 3)
    - "Zig Zags": 3rd annual parade poster, 1882 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook pertaining to Yale: clippings, exams, invitations, programs, 1885-1893 (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1854, 1933; Accession 2009-M-042
  - Photograph of David Howland (B.A. 1933) in a football uniform (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Framed senior picture of Henry Elias Howland (B.A. 1854) (Box 1, Folder 2)